Register of the National Right to Work Committee issuances
Hoover Institution Archives
National Right to Work Committee issuances
1952-1981
1955-1981
81126
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.7 linear feet)
The issuances of the National Right to Work Committee consist of newsletters, bulletins, leaflets, pamphlets, speeches, testimony, articles, and press releases relating to labor unions and right-to-work laws in the United States.
National Right to Work Committee.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
The National Right to Work Committee, founded in 1955, is a non-profit organization of employees and employers opposing compulsory union membership in the United States and defending the right of citizens to work, regardless of their union status. The Committee seeks to inform citizens about the right-to-work movement through the use of various educational materials, including newsletters, press releases, literature and books, seminars, speakers, radio series, and motion pictures. Additionally, the Committee works to support statewide and national movements to enact right-to-work legislation and uphold Section 14(b) of the Taft-Hartley Act, which affirms that states may have right-to-work laws.
Scope and Content of Collection
The bulk of the records in this collection span the years 1955 to 1981 and include newsletters, bulletins, leaflets, pamphlets, speeches, testimony, articles, and press releases relating to labor unions and right-to-work laws in the United States. The collection largely consists of materials published by the National Right to Work Committee to promote its ideals and educate the public, as well as speeches and testimony given by members of the Committee and right-to-work supporters. This outward-facing material was designed to raise awareness about compulsory unionism and right-to-work laws. Exceptions include some informational pamphlets about the Committee, its work, and its educational efforts, as well as some collected materials from outside sources documenting issues of interest to the Committee.
Where possible, the original order (generally chronological) was maintained. In the instance of the materials received in the pamphlets category, which had no original order, series and subseries were created, and the materials were arranged by subject. Additionally, with the speeches by right-to-work supporters, a decision was made to arrange them first by speaker and then chronologically, in order to collocate the speeches of individuals, particularly since there were a large number of speeches by Charles W. Bailey, who held various positions on the National Right to Work Committee Board.
Labor unions--United States.; Open and closed shop--United States.
- Newsletters, 1955-1981 (Box 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of newsletters published by the National Right to Work Committee, arranged alphabetically by title, then chronologically. The Right to Work National Newsletter became the National Right to Work Newsletter in June 1969. Similarly, the NRW News Service became the Right to Work News Service in March 1975.
  - Free Choice, 1965-1981 (Box-folder 1: 1-4)
    1965 - 2nd Quarter, 1981. Per note from donor, May - December 1978 and January - April 1979 issues are not included. 1969 No. 10 is missing.
  - National Right to Work Newsletter, June 1969-1981 (Box-folder 1: 5-7, Box-folder 2: 1-3)
    Through October 29, 1981.
  - Right to Work National Newsletter, 1955-May 1969 (Box-folder 2: 3-7)
    Missing 1955 Vol. 1, No. 4; 1956 Vol. 2, Nos. 2, 3, and 5; 1962 Vol. 8, No. 2.
  - Right to Work News Service, March 1975-1981 (Box-folder 2: 8, Box-folder 3: 1)
    Through September, 1981. Per note from donor, in 1978 there was no #11 issued.
  - NRW News Service, 1970-February 1975 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
    1970s issues are undated, so original order is unknown. Missing 1971 #3. Per note from donor, 1973 #9, 11, 17, 21 and 25 are not included.
  - Recaps, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    Published by Concerned Educators Against Forced Unionism, a division of the National Right to Work Committee.
  - Samples of other NRWC publications, 1963-1981 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Includes AFL-CIO News, Right to Work News, Right to Work Digest, Issue Briefing Paper, and Violence Task Force Report.
- Larson, Reed -- Speeches, articles, interviews, 1959-1979 (Box 3-4)
  General note
  See also: Pamphlets -- Larson, Reed speeches, Box 6, folder 6.
  Consists mainly of speeches given by Larson, former President of the National Right to Work Committee, to various clubs and associations across the United States, arranged chronologically.
  - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - 1972-1975 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - 1968-1971 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - 1959-1967 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Speeches by right-to-work supporters, 1959-1980 (Box 4)
  Consists of speeches given mostly by National Right to Work Committee Board members to various conventions and groups across the United States, arranged alphabetically by speaker, then chronologically if necessary. There are only one or two speeches for each individual, with the exception of Charles W. Bailey.
  - Bailey, Charles W., 1969-1980 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Bailey, Charles W., 1965-1968; Cadwallader, S.D.; Calvin, Ben; Dillard, E.S. (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Hooser, Lafayette A.; Kilcullen, John; Newton, Hugh C.; Ruggles, William (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Legislative testimony statements, 1965-1981 (Box 4-5)
  Consists of statements given before Congress or submitted as part of the Congressional record by Reed Larson and various right to work supporters, arranged chronologically.
  - 1978-1981 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - 1977 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - 1973-1974 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 1969-1972 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 1965-1968 (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Factual sources, 1960s - 1970s (Box-folder 5: 4)
  Consists of bibliographies, newspaper article documentation for the Committee’s film And Women Must Weep, and the results of public opinion research about right-to-work laws conducted in 1964 and from 1974-1977.
- Collected materials, 1952-1977 (Box 5-6)
  Consists of materials from outside sources, such as newspaper articles and pamphlets, relating to compulsory unionism and right-to-work laws, divided into subseries by subject.
  - Chavez, Cesar and California agricultural workers' labor dispute, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Information about, and in support of, right-to-work laws, 1956-1969 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    Pamphlets: If You Couldn't Vote in Free Elections; The Voluntarism of Samuel Gompers [2 versions]; The Union Label and Its Use or Nonuse on Printed Materials
    Articles: "The Case for Boulwarism;" "The Right to Work Legal Defense Foundation - A Force in the Public Sector;" "The Aerospace Story;" "Kennedy Urged to Fire 'Biased' Aerospace Aide" / "Douglas Employes [sic] File Suit"
    Copy of complaint in E.R. Reid, et al. v. McDonnell Douglas Corporation and UAW-AFL-CIO District Lodge 1093
  - National Association of Manufacturers pamphlets, 1959, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Negative effects of compulsory unionism, 1950s, 1970s (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Pamphlets from state right-to-work movements, 1958-1977 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Political and legislative aspects of the right to work and compulsory unionism, 1956-1977 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Religion and the right to work, 1955-1965, 1975 (Box-folder 6: 2)
- Pamphlets, 1955-1981 (Box 7)
  Consists of pamphlets published by the National Right to Work Committee, divided into subseries by subject.
  These include both informational pamphlets about various aspects of compulsory unionism and right-to-work laws, as well as advertisements for the Committee’s own educational materials and pamphlets describing the Committee and its work.
  - About the NRWC and its educational materials, 1958-1981 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Arguments in support of right-to-work laws, 1958-1966 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Benefits of right-to-work laws, 1958-1979 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Compulsory unionism and public/government employees, 1969-1978 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Condemnation of compulsory unions and their tactics, 1955-1980 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Larson, Reed speeches, 1965-1978 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    See also: Larson, Reed -- Speeches, articles, interviews, Box 3, folders 6-8, and Box 4, folders 1-2.
  - Political and legislative aspects of the right to work and compulsory unionism, 1959-1979 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Political cartoons, 1965, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Religion and the right to work, 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Text of state right-to-work laws, 1958, 1972 (Box-folder 7: 10)